Guide to the Land of Zenj Photograph Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Thematic collections, 1875-1925; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Other East African churches and missions: 40 photographs (Box 6, Folder 43-45)
    - 27. Untitled [Lutheran Church in Dar es Salaam]. C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., 1902; 23.5 x 17.5 cm.
    - 28. "Ev. Kirche Innere-Ansicht." C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., 1902; 23.5 x 17.5 cm.
    - 29. "Ev. Kirche mit Pfarrhaus." C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., 1902; 23.5 x 17.5 cm.
    - 30. "Kath. Mission. Eingang." C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., 1902; 23.5 x 17.5 cm.
    - 31. Untitled [View of Catholic Church in Dar es Salaam]. C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., 1903; 23.5 x 17.5 cm.
    - 32. "Ev. Mission. Seeseite." C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., 1897; 23.5 x 17.5 cm.
    - 33. "Ev. Mission. Landseite." C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., 1897; 23.5 x 17.5 cm.
    - 34. "Kath. Mission. Schwestern-haus." C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., 1898; 23.5 x 17.5 cm.
    - 35. "Erstkommunikanten v. St. Maria. Dar es Salaam." C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., 1900; 23.5 x 17.5 cm.
    - 36. "Exped. Der Kath. Missions-Schwestern nach Iringa." C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., circa 1900; 23.5 x 17.5 cm.
    - 37. "Kath. Mission. Kullasini." C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., 1900; 23.5 x 17.5 cm.
    - 38. "Kath. Kirchen-Einweihung. 4.II.1903." C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., 23.5 x 17.5 cm.
    - 39. "Mission Schule." C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., 1897; 23.5 x 17.5 cm.
    - 40. "Königs-Palme. Landschaftbilder in Missionsgarten in Bagamoyo." C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., 1898; 23.5 x 17.5 cm.
  - Ngomas and Siku-Kuu: Two Forms of Celebration: 5 photographs (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - 1. "Ngoma Tanz. N.1." C. Vincenti., circa 1901; 22.4 x 17 cm.
      On verso: "Blik von Ev. Mission bus. N. I., Dar-es-salaam." from Ports and Other Places, German East Africa, Dar es Salaam.
    - 2. "Maskirte Suahili - Weiber beim Ngomatanz." C. Vincenti., 1901; 22.8 x 16.8 cm.
      On verso: "Klubhaus Daressalaam." from Ports and Other Places, German East Africa, Dar es Salaam.
    - 3. Ten Ngoma Dancers. L. M. Santos, Photographer., circa 1900; 21 x 15.2 cm.
    - 4. "Ramathan festival Siku-Kuu." Unidentified photographer., 1890s; 18.5 x 14.5 cm.
    - 5. Untitled. Siku-Kuu. A large Swahili crowd at a funfair, Zanzibar. Coutinho Brothers., circa 1900; 20.5 x 15 cm.
  - Aspects of German Colonial Life: 35 photographs, 3 (Box 6, Folder 47-49)
    - 1. "Ochsen-gespan." C. Vincenti., 1890?; 22.4 x 16.4 cm.
    - 2. Untitled [Two German officials in front of wagon]. C. Vincenti., 1890; 22.5 x 17 cm.
    - 3. Untitled [Posed group of four Germans in uniform]. C. Vicente?, 1890s; 22.2 x 16.6 cm.
    - 4. "Karavanserei - Wohnung bis 10.6.1904. Träge zum Abmarsch bereit. Bagamoyo." Unidentified photographer., 21.2 x 15 cm.
      On verso: 5. "Mein Komtor. Bagamoyo 1904."
    - 5. "Mein Komtor. Bagamoyo 1904." Unidentified photographer., 20.2 x 15 cm.
      On recto: 4. "Karavanserei - Wohnung bis 10.6.1904. Träge zum Abmarsch bereit. Bagamoyo."
    - 6. "Parade zm 27.I.93 in Dar-es-Salâm." Unidentified photographer., 1893; 18 x 13 cm.
    - 7. Untitled half-plate. Unidentified photographer., 1890s; 16.5 x 12.0 cm.
    - 8. "Gemütliche Sitzung." Unidentified photographer., 1904; 23.2 x 17.5 cm.
      On verso: 9. "Weinprobe. 17.7.1904."
    - 9. "Weinprobe. 17.7.1904." Unidentified photographer., 23.2 x 17.5 cm.
      On recto: 8. "Gemütliche Sitzung."
    - 10. "Oberst Excellency v. Schele mit seinen Dienern." Unidentified photographer., 1890s; 20.3 x 14.8 cm.
    - 11. "Les zebras du President de Dar es Salaam." Unidentified photographer., circa 1890; 20 x 14.5 cm.
    - 12. "__?elfahrt 1908." Unidentified photographer., 17 x 12 cm.
    - 13. "__?elfahrt 1908." Unidentified photographer., 11.2 x 12 cm.
    - 14. "Herr Wassermann." Unidentified photographer., circa 1910; 12 x 17 cm.
    - 15. Untitled [German in rickshaw]. Unidentified photographer., circa 1908; 18 x 13 cm.
    - 16. Untitled [Three Germans, dressed in formal white, seated in rattan chairs]. Unidentified photographer., circa 1910; 17 x 12 cm.
    - 17. Untitled [Seated European man holding a chained leopard between his legs]. Unidentified photographer., circa 1908; 17 x 12 cm.
    - 18. Untitled [European man with chained leopard]. Unidentified photographer., circa 1908; 17 x 12 cm.
    - 19. "Unser Hof mit Lager..." Unidentified photographer., circa 1910; 17 x 12 cm.
    - 20. "Strandpartie b. Daressalam." Unidentified photographer., circa 1890; 16.5 x 12 cm.
    - 21. Untitled [Three Germans on the beach]. Unidentified photographer., circa 1890; 16.5 x 12 cm.
    - 22. Untitled [A young elephant with two Europeans]. Unidentified photographer., circa 1910; 17 x 12 cm.
    - 23. Untitled [All-male dinner party]. Unidentified photographer., circa 1908; 22 x 17 cm.
    - 24. Untitled [German soldier in uniform]. Unidentified photographer., 1890s; 12 x 17 cm.
    - 25. Untitled [German soldier in uniform]. Unidentified photographer., 1890s; 12 x 17 cm.
    - 26. Untitled [German soldier with saddled camel]. Unidentified photographer., 1890s; 11 x 16.5 cm.
    - 27. [German soldiers on camels]. Unidentified photographer., 1890s; 17.4 x 12.5 cm.
    - 28. Untitled [Big-game hunter with dead hippopotamus]. Unidentified photographer., 1890s; 17 x 12.2 cm.
    - 29. "5m Krokodil, erlegt am Rufiyi im Juni 1913." Unidentified photographer., 14.8 x 10.2 cm.
    - 30. Büfeel, erlegt am Rufiyi 31/8.13." Unidentified photographer., 1913; 15 x 10 cm.
    - 31. [A big-game hunting party of thirteen Germans and their African guides]. Unidentified photographer., circa 1910; 17 x 12 cm.
    - 32. Untitled [Two Germans on safari]. Unidentified photographer., 1913; 14.5 x 9.8 cm.
    - 33. Untitled [German holding up a long-tailed monkey for display]. Unidentified photographer., 1913; 9.7 x 14.5 cm.
    - 34. "Vor dem Abmarsch nach Usambara/Tanganjika/See 99 Tagesmärsche...Aug. 1906." C. Vincent. Dar-es-Salaam., 22.7 x 16.7 cm.
    - 35. Untitled [Group of eighteen German Army Non-Commissioned Officers in full-dress uniform]. Unidentified photographer., circa 1906; 31.5 x 21.3 cm.
- People, 1890-1900; Series V; 0.21; (1 box)
  Material in this series corresponds to that described in Chapter Four of the dealer catalog.
  - Studio portraits and posed groups, circa 1890-1900 (Box 7, Folder 50-56)
  - Informal portrayals of groups and individuals, circa 1890-1896 (Box 7, Folder 57-60)
- Ports and other places, 1885-1920; Series VI; 0.84; (3 boxes)
  Material in this series corresponds to that described in Chapter Five of the dealer catalog.
  - German East Africa., circa 1890-1920
    - Dar es Salaam: 88 photographs (Box 8, Folder 61-67)
    - Bagamoyo: 15 photographs, circa 1885-1898 (Box 8, Folder 68-69)
    - Kilwa-Kisiwani: 19 photographs, circa 1890-1901 (Box 8, Folder 70-71)
    - Tanga: 12 photographs, circa 1900 (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - Mikindani: 9 photographs, 1902 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Other places: 21 photographs, circa 1890-1903 (Box 8, Folder 74-75)
    - In the countryside: 42 photographs, circa 1896-1910 (Box 9, Folder 76-79)
  - Portuguese East Africa, 1895-1910
    - Group I: 6 photographs, 1900-1910 (Box 9, Folder 80)
    - Group II: 3 photographs, 1912 (Box 9, Folder 81)
    - Group III: 8 photographs, circa 1900-1910 (Box 9, Folder 82)
    - Group IV: 27 photographs, circa 1903-10, undated (Box 9, Folder 83-85)
    - Group V: 4 photographs, circa 1908-1910
  - British Protectorate of Zanzibar (including the Coastal Strip)
    - Mombasa: 14 photographs, circa 1890-1905 (Box 9, Folder 86)
    - Zanzibar Town and Other, circa 1890-1910 (Box 9, Folder 87-88)
  - Empty cases, undated (Box 10, Folder 89-90)
- Magic Lantern Slides, 1895-1910; Series VII; 3.15; (5 boxes)
  Material in this series corresponds to that which is described in Chapter Six of the dealer catalog.
  - East Africa and Zanzibar, circa 1904-1910 (Box 11, Folder 91)
    A group of thirty (plus one duplicate) glass-mounted, magic lantern slides, some in color, the remainder in monochrome; each 7.5 x 7 cm. and depicting people and scenes in East Africa and Zanzibar. This group was put together from diverse sources, including Underwood and Underwood, by the Bureau of Visual Instruction, Chicago, Public Schools.
  - Metal and glass lens for an antique lantern projector, contained in its original cardboard box, undated (Box 11, Folder 92)
  - German East Africa (1 of 3), circa 1895-1910 (Box 12, Folder 93)
    A group of one hundred and fifty magic lantern slides housed in three partitioned boxes made of wood. A large majority of the slides are labelled "Walter Grimm, Photo-Werkstätten Dresden, Grunaer Strasse 3." Others are labelled: "Photozentrale des Kolonialkriegerdank G.m.b.H Berlin NW.6, Karlstr. 31." The images appear to be the work of more than one unidentified photographer, and Walter Grimm and Photozentrale seem to have been the makers of the slides. The images depict a wide range of places and scenes of life in German East Africa.
  - German East Africa (2 of 3), circa 1895-1910 (Box 13, Folder 94)
  - German East Africa (3 of 3), circa 1895-1910 (Box 14, Folder 95)
  - Lantern Projector, stored in briefcase (Box 15, Folder 96)
- The Voyage Out (and Back) Through the Suez Canal, 1869-1937; Series VIII
  Material in this series corresponds to that described in Chapter Seven of the dealer catalog.
  - On the Suez Canal: 44 photographs, circa 1869-1930
  - Aden: 14 photographs, circa 1890-1910
  - Djibouti: 24 photographs, circa 1890-1900
  - Sheets 1-7, 1936-37
- Oversize, 12.56; (11 boxes)
  - East Africa, Zanzibar and Aden: 1 photograph album (in Series II) (Box 16, Folder 97)
  - Eastern Africa: 1 photograph album (in Series II) (Box 17, Folder 98)
  - German East Africa: 1 photograph album (in Series II) (Box 17, Folder 99)
  - German East Africa: 1 photograph album (in Series II) (Box 18, Folder 100)
  - Portuguese East Africa and the British Central African Protectorate: 1 photograph album (in Series II) (Box 19, Folder 101)
  - Portuguese East Africa, Zanzibar, Aden: 1 photograph album (in Series II) (Box 19, Folder 102)
  - Portuguese East Africa, Mozambique: 38 photographs with related printed material (in Series II) (Box 20, Folder 103-109)
  - Uganda: 1 photograph album (in Series II) (Box 21, Folder 110)
  - Zanzibar and Pemba: 1 photograph album (in Series II) (Box 21, Folder 111)
  - Hansing & Company. Zanzibar: 1 photograph album (in Series II) (Box 22, Folder 112)
  - P. De Lord - Dar es Salaam and Zanzibar (in Series III) (Box 23, Folder 113)
  - Panoramas (in Series III) (Box 24, Folder 114)
  - German East Africa, Other places (in Series VI) (Box 24, Folder 114)
  - British Protectorate of Zanzibar, Zanzibar Town and Other (in Series VI) (Box 24, Folder 114)
  - Walther Dobbertin-German East Africa (in Series III) (Box 24, Folder 115)
  - J. and J. & M. Lazarus-Portuguese East Africa (in Series III) (Box 24, Folder 116)
  - Portuguese East Africa-Group V (in Series VI) (Box 24, Folder 116)
  - K. Ledermann-Zanzibar (in Series III) (Box 24, Folder 117)
  - Zanzibar-The Sultan's palaces, Before August, 1896 (in Series IV) (Box 24, Folder 117)
  - British protectorate of Zanzibar, Zanzibar Town and Other (in Series VI) (Box 24, Folder 117)
  - Zanzibar-Four sultans and a would-be usurper (in Series IV) (Box 25, Folder 118)
  - Zanzibar-The Sultan's palaces, British Bombardment and "The Shortest War in History" (in Series IV) (Box 25, Folder 118)
  - Zanzibar-Four sultans and a would-be usurper (in Series IV) (Box 25, Folder 119)
  - Zanzibar-Four sultans and a would-be usurper (in Series IV) (Box 25, Folder 120)
  - Slave-Trade in East Africa (in Series IV) (Box 25, Folder 121)
  - British Protectorate of Zanzibar, Zanzibar Town and Other (in Series VI) (Box 25, Folder 121)
  - Ngomas and Siku-Kuu: two forms of celebration (in Series IV) (Box 25, Folder 121)
  - Zanzibar-The Sultan's palaces, Before August, 1896 (in Series IV) (Box 25, Folder 121)
  - Zanzibar-The Sultan's palaces, The Rebuilt Palace (in Series IV) (Box 25, Folder 121)
  - Zanzibar-The Sultan's palaces, Palace Parades and Ceremonies (in Series IV) (Box 25, Folder 121)
  - Aspects of German colonial life (in Series IV) (Box 25, Folder 122)
  - German East Africa, Dar es Salaam (in Series VI) (Box 25, Folder 122)
  - Studio portraits and posed groups (in Series V) (Box 25, Folder 123)
  - German East Africa, Dar es Salaam (in Series VI) (Box 25, Folder 123)
  - German East Africa, In the countryside (in Series VI) (Box 25, Folder 124)
  - British Protectorate of Zanzibar, Zanzibar Town and Other (in Series VI) (Box 25, Folder 125)
  - On the Suez Canal (in Series VIII) (Box 26, Folder 126)
  - Aden (in Series VIII) (Box 26, Folder 127)
  - British Protectorate of Zanzibar, Mombasa (in Series VI) (Box 26, Folder 127)
  - Djibouti (in Series VIII) (Box 26, Folder 128)
  - British Protectorate of Zanzibar, Zanzibar Town and Other (in Series VI) (Box 26, Folder 128)
  - Sheets 1-7 (in Series VIII) (Box 26, Folder 129)